A Guide to the Papers of the Virginia Credit Union League 1923-1991
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Virginia Credit Union League 1923-1991
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11102
ca. 16,000 items
This collection consists of ca. 16,000 items, 1923-1991, and contains correspondence, printed material, minutes, and related materials, much of which was formerly housed in three-ring notebooks (probably by the League Historian and Editor of The Virginian, Jack O'Connor), all pertaining to the history and operations of the Virginia Credit Union League. The Virginia Credit Union League was organized on November 26, 1934, and became incorporated in 1952.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library on July 26, 1993, by Eugene Farley, President of the Virginia Credit Union League, Lynchburg, Virginia, through William Wilkerson, Assistant Provost for Research, University of Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 16,000 items, 1923-1991, and contains correspondence, printed material, minutes, and related materials, much of which was formerly housed in three-ring notebooks (probably by the League Historian and Editor of The Virginian, Jack O'Connor), all pertaining to the history and operations of the Virginia Credit Union League. The Virginia Credit Union League was organized on November 26, 1934, and became incorporated in 1952.
The League was founded "to promote the organization and development of credit unions in Virginia, to represent the credit unions on a state and national basis, to originate favorable legislation and to guard against attacks on present laws, to provide advice and counsel in the development of local credit union chapters, to maintain a state-wide publication for the dissemination of information for credit union operations, and to maintain a central source for the dissemination of information about applicable governmental laws and regulations."
The collection is arranged in two series, 1) Minutes and Credit Union League History Papers and 2) Miscellaneous Topical Files re the Virginia Credit Union League. The first series, 1953-1991, arranged in reverse chronological order within the year, comprises the material found in three-ring binders and consists of the minutes of the Board of Directors meetings, the Executive Committee meetings, Education Committee meetings, other occasional committee meetings, and the Annual Conventions, including minutes of the Virginia League Central Credit Union; notices and bulletins; reports of various committees; treasurer's reports and financial summaries; printed material; statements concerning policies and objectives; reports of the managing director; issues of the official publication for the V.C.U.L., The Virginian; correspondence; copies of addresses and speeches; memoranda; agendas for meetings; nominations; rosters of Virginia Credit Union officers; notes concerning the V.C.U.L. meetings kept by Jack O'Connor; and credit union memorabilia.
Many of these records in the first series were assembled to help compile an updated history of the Virginia Credit Union League. In about 1968, Jack O'Connor, a member of the League Education Committee for a total of twenty years, was appointed League Historian. O'Connor wrote several long-time activists in the credit union, such as Managing Director Eugene H. Farley, Jr., Dollie Reynolds (a League Director), C.L. Shackelford (League President 1952-1953, President of the Danville Chapter, and former editor of The Virginian), and E.L. Field (League President 1936-1937), asking for their help in assembling earlier League records into a new history to supplement E.L. Field's Virginia Credit Union League History 1922-1954(see Box 29). O'Connor was a very active volunteer in the Virginia Credit Union League, Editor of The Virginian, President of the Tidewater Chapter of the Credit Union, a founding father and the only President of the St. Pius X Federal Credit Union until his death in 1979. O'Connor's history was never published in book form but appeared in monthly historical segments in The Virginian.
The second series consists of miscellaneous topical files pertaining to the V.C.U.L. (Boxes 22-32). Among these are the correspondence and records kept by E.L. Field (Boxes 24-26), 1923-1966, arranged in chronological order, dating from Field's (d. 1973) election as president of the Richmond Postal Credit Union, the first successful credit union in Virginia, on September 7, 1923. These records are used frequently for the earliest years covered in the latest history of the Virginia Credit Union League, Of the People, By the People, and For the People by William R. Wilkerson (1993). Topics in these papers include the Welfare Council; co-operative buying; the Local Service Council; the establishment of credit unions in Petersburg, Norfolk, Roanoke, and elsewhere; the use of the credit union to purchase economical group life insurance policies; the extension of credit unions to other postal employee groups; a copy of the 1934 application for membership in the Credit Union National Association (CUNA), with Field elected Vice-President of the Virginia Credit Union League, and the first meeting of the Board of Directors.
Correspondents of Field include: Henry S. Dennison (First Director of the United States Post Office Department of Service Relations Division); Louis Brehm (Assistant Director of the Service Relations Division); Roy F. Bergengren (1879-1955), the executive secretary of the Credit Union National Extension Bureau until 1934, when there were enough credit union associations on the state level to organize the Credit Union National Association (CUNA) - Bergengren became its managing director (until his retirement in 1945); E.G. Swem; Angela Melville; J.C. Cotten; M.E. Bristow (Chief Examiner of Banks, State Corporation Commission); and Howard T. Colvin.
Committees with files in this series include the Advertising (Marketing) Committee; the Education Committee; the Legislative and Liaison Committee; the Planning Committee; and the Policy Committee. Individual files on the Virginia Credit Union League Conventions begin with the Fourteenth Annual Convention held at the Mosque, Richmond, Virginia, on May 29, 1948, and continue into the seventies. Records for the annual conventions are also filed by date in the first series of minutes and league history papers.
Printed Material with individual folders include "The Little Man Says" an education-oriented newsletter, named after the credit union symbol of the little man carrying an umbrella; notices and bulletins; copies of The Virginian and folders on reporters for the publication (copies of this publication can also be found in the first series by date); and miscellaneous printed items pertaining to the credit union movement (Box 28) including newsletters from North Carolina, early copies of The Virginian(1946 Oct-Nov; 1947 Apr; 1949 Feb); copies of the Credit Union Bridge (1955 Oct; 1959 Feb); reprinted addresses by Edward A. Filene (1860-1937), a leader of the progressive reform movement in Boston; and The Debt Shall Die With the Debtor The CUNA Mutual Insurance Society Story by Charles F. Eikel, Jr.
Other items in the second series include blank examples of checklists and forms used by credit unions; reports about the credit union; a file on the Chapter Leaders Seventh Annual Conference; and the CUNA School for Credit Union Personnel Lecture Outlines belonging to Garland K. Keeling (1918-1967) who became managing director of the V.C.U.L. in 1949, serving for seventeen and half years until his death in 1967. There are also records of the Virginia League Central Credit Union, 1964-1973, "a state-wide credit union for members of affiliated credit unions offering services unavailable locally," in individual folders (Box 30) as well as mixed in with the other minutes in the first series by date. All of the various League histories by Field and O'Connor, with copies of research material and notes for use in the history, can be found in Box 29. Also present in this series is a file about Virginia Credit Union Services, Incorporated, founded to provide electronic data processing and other contract services to credit unions and the papers of the Tidewater Chapter of the V.C.U.L., 1964-1965, when Jack O'Connor was President and Vice-President.
Contents List
- Series I: Minutes and Credit Union League History Papers 1953-1991 (Box 1-21)
  - Minutes and League History Papers 1953-1991 (Box 1-21)
    1953-1962--Box 1 (10 folders)
    1963-1967--Box 2 (8 folders)
    1968-1970 Jun--Box 3 (7 folders)
    1970 Jul-1971 Sep--Box 4 (6 folders)
    1971 Oct-1972--Box 5 (6 folders)
    1973--Box 6 (5 folders)
    1974--Box 7 (6 folders)
    1975--Box 8 (6 folders)
    1976-1977 Feb--Box 9 (7 folders)
    1977 Mar-Sep--Box 10 (7 folders)
    1977 Oct-1978 Apr--Box 11 (8 folders)
    1978 May-Dec--Box 12 (7 folders)
    1979-1981--Box 13 (8 folders)
    1982-1983 Jun--Box 14 (6 folders)
    1983 Jul-1984--Box 15 (6 folders)
    1985-1986 Feb--Box 16 (7 folders)
    1986 Mar-1987 Jun--Box 17 (7 folders)
    1987 Jul-1988 Sep--Box 18 (7 folders)
    1988 Oct-1989--Box 19 (6 folders)
    1990--Box 20 (5 folders)
    1991--Box 21 (5 folders)
  - Minutes and League History Papers--Critiques of Credit Union Newsletters and Annual Reports 1975 Apr (Box 8)
- Series II: Miscellaneous Files re The Virginia Credit Union League 1929-1990, n.d. (Box 22-32)
  - Advertising Committee 1980-1981 (Box 22)
  - Advertising Committee--Credit Union National Association Communications Recommendation 1981 (Box 22)
  - Advertising Committee--Survey n.d. (Box n.d.)
  - Advertising Committee--Texas Credit Union League and Affiliates Information re Marketing 1980 (Box 22)
  - Chapter Leaders' Conference--Seventh Annual 1964 Oct 23-24 (Box 22)
  - Check List & Forms re Organization and First Board Meeting--State Chartered Credit Unions n.d. (Box 22)
  - Conventions 1948-1972, 1979, 13 folders (Box 22-24)
    1948-1958: Box 22 (3 folders)
    1959-1970: Box 23 (8 folders)
    1971-1972, 1979: Box 24 (2 folders)
  - Correspondence and Records kept by E.L. Field 1923-1944, 1952-1953, 1966, 20 folders (Box 24-26)
    1923-1928: Box 25 (7 folders)
    1929-1938 Aug: Box 25 (8 folders)
    1938 Sep-1944, 1952-1953, 1966: Box 26 (5 folders)
  - CUNA School for Credit Union Personnel Lecture Outlines belonging to Garland K. Keeling 1956, 2 folders (Box 26)
  - "Custom Analysis of Virginia Credit Union League and Affiliates" conducted by A.W. Jordan, Robert W. Hood, and Brad Murphy 1977 Dec (Box 26)
  - Education Committee 1978-1979, 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Federal Credit Union Organization 1972 (Box 27)
  - Forms Used by Credit Unions n.d. (Box 27)
  - Information Booklet Distributed to Virginia Credit Unions For Internal Use to Answer Charges and Accusations Made by the Banking Industry 1990 Jan 25 (Box 27)
  - Legislative and Liaison Committee 1959-1971 (Box 27)
  - "The Little Man Says" Newletters, including its predecessor Credit Union News 1952-1964 (Box 27)
  - Loan Policy Questionnaire sent out by Jack O'Connor of The Virginian to Credit Unions 1977 Nov (Box 27)
  - Miscellany File of Humorous Stories, Etc. ca. 1964, 1968-1970, n.d. (Box 28)
  - Notices and Bulletins 1962-1973, 2 folders (Box 28)
  - Planning Committee--CUNA 1965 (Box 28)
  - Planning Committee--Handbook, Report & Seminar ca. 1978 (Box 28)
  - Policy Committee 1971 (Box 28)
  - Printed Material--Miscellaneous 1924-1982, n.d. (Box 28)
  - Report re Virginia Credit Union Services in the ElectronicFunds Transfers Environement 19776-1981 by Auerbach Associates, Inc. 1977 Mar 16 (Box 28)
  - Reporters for The Virginian 1969-1973, 3 folders (Box 28)
  - Stabilization Fund & Share Insurance 1960-1971 (Box 29)
  - Tidewater Chapter of the Virginia Credit Union League 1964-1965 (Box 29)
  - Truth in Lending Law 1969 (Box 29)
  - Virginia Credit Union League History 1922-1954 compiled by Edward L. Field 1956 (Box 29)
  - "Virginia Credit Union League History 1953-1958 Volume II" compiled by Jack O'Connor 1970-1971 (Box 29)
  - Virginia Credit Union League History--Research Materials & Notes, including Copies 1914-1932, 1967-1979, n.d., 3 folders (Box 29)
  - Virginia Credit Union Services Corporation, Inc. 1969-1974 (Box 30)
  - Virginia Leage Central Credit Union 1964-1973, 9 folders (Box 30)
  - The Virginian News of Credit Unions in the Old Dominion ca. 1950-1959, 1961-1979, 7 folders (Box 31)
  - The Virginian: Editor's Production Copies with Correspondence and Other Material 1966-1971, 1974-1975, 5 folders (Box 32)
  - Yearbook--Hampton Roads Chapter 1965-1966, 1975-1976 (Box 32)